Jaspreet Ranjit

Ronald Tutor Hall 420 3710 McClintock Ave Los Angeles, CA 90089 jranjit@usc.edu (703)973-7665

https://jr4fs.github.io/

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am a Ph.D. student at the University of Southern California Viterbi School of Engineering advised by **Prof. Swabha Swayamdipta** and a member of **Center for AI** in **Society**. Previously, I was a Research Assistant in the **Vision, Language and Learning Lab**, working with **Prof. Vicente Ordóñez** on exploring biases in visual recognition models. I am interested in topics of bias and fairness in language models.

EDUCATION

University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA

Ph.D. Student, Computer Science - NLP Advisor: Prof. Swabha Swayamdipta

University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA

Master of Science, Computer Science, December 2021

Advisor: Prof. Vicente Ordóñez

Thesis: Analyzing Gender Biases in Visual Recognition Models

Relevant Courses: Machine Learning, Vision and Language, Natural Language Processing, Algorithms, Cloud Computing, Geometry of Data, Machine Learning in Image

Analysis

University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, May 2021 Rodman Scholar: Top 5% of Engineering Class

Relevant Courses: Computer Science - Python, Java & C++/C, Analysis of Algorithms, Theory of Computation, Computer Architecture, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Human Computer Interaction in Software Development, Operating Systems, Probability, Linear Algebra, Ordinary Differential Equations

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Data, Interpretability, Language and Learning Lab (DILL) Los Angeles, CA Graduate Research Assistant Fall 2022 - Present

Advisor: Prof. Swabha Swayamdipta

Machine Learning Research Assistant

Focus: My research interests lie in investigating societal biases in datasets, measuring the propagation of such biases learned by models in downstream tasks and reasoning about the broader implications of fairness in applications of NLP for social good.

The Vision, Language and Learning Lab at UVA

Charlottesville, VA Nov 2020 - July 2022

Advisor: Prof. Vicente Ordóñez

Focus: Developing a tool in Pytorch that analyzes the implicit feature representations of visual recognition models such as vision transformers and convolutional neural networks with respect to bias in datasets such as Coco and Openimages. This tool allows for comparison of implicit feature representations across different models and synthesizes this data for convenient comparison. Analyzed the impact of model characteristics such as: pretraining dataset, network architecture, and training setting on the

representation of gender biases in the feature space. In collaboration with Columbia University: Prof. Baishakhi Ray *Thesis*

UVA Engineering Link Lab

Charlottesville, VA Aug 2019 - Nov 2020

Machine Learning Research Assistant

Advisor: Prof. Madhur Behl

Focus: Proposed a certification scheme to determine the level of safety and reliability which allows for safe market introduction of autonomous vehicles. Performed natural language processing analysis on caption data from Berkeley Deep Drive Dataset to extract high-level representations of traffic scenario videos. Aggregated the Traf-

fic Scenario Similarity Dataset (TSS) which contains human ranking annotations for similarity between traffic scenarios. Prototyped multi-modal transformer networks in Pytorch for tagging traffic videos with labels. *Project Site*

UVA Aerospace Engineering Research Group

Charlottesville, VA

Machine Learning Research Assistant

Oct 2017 - Aug 2019

Advisor: Prof. David Sheffler

Focus: Developed a prototype of a 3D printed UAV that completes a mission autonomously using a Raspberry Pi and Pixhawk companion computer and designed machine learning programs for object recognition and communication in OpenCV for precise missions.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Vimeo New York, NY

Machine Learning Researcher on Search and Recommendations Jun 2021 - Aug 2021

Mentor: Silvena Chan

Analyzed gender biases in search and recommendation system and formulated a bias identification framework with the Rank Bias metric quantifying gender biases in ranked search results. Developed learning to rank (LTR) models in Pytorch using RankNet and LambdaMART, and developed an internal dataset for LTR models in private search. Worked with big data in Snowflake and wrote queries in SQL to scale bias experiments. Medium Publication

Minimally Invasive Spinal Technology

Charlottesville, VA

Machine Learning Engineer and SWE Lead

Oct 2019 - Aug 2020

Mentor: Alexander Singh

Worked as a lead Machine Learning Researcher to develop machine learning algorithms in Pytorch and Keras for the analysis and prediction of scoliosis using Unet++ and Centernet. Deployed this model for medical testing using Docker, AWS and Django.

Expedition Technology

Herndon, VA

 $Machine\ Learning\ Researcher$

Dec 2019 - Jan 2020

Mentor: Andrew Draganov

Researched novel semi-supervised framework for detecting out-of-distribution inputs. Implemented the OpenMax algorithm: a methodology to adapt deep networks for open set recognition - estimates the probability of an input being from an unknown class in Tensorflow. Investigated existing literature in the domain of Open Set Recognition and performed A-B testing.

Expedition Technology

Herndon, VA

Machine Learning Engineer

Jun 2019 - Aug 2019

Mentor: Cheryl Daner

Researched anchorless object detection techniques for 3D point cloud object detection. Designed a convolutional neural network on the basis of existing VoxelNet and Center-Net architectures in Tensorflow. Summary of Work

NASA Goddard Spaceflight Center

Greenbelt, MD

 $Core\ Flight\ Software\ Engineer$

Jun 2018 - Aug 2018

Mentor: Alessandro Geist

Developed and benchmarked core Flight Software apps in C/C++ that directed AI image processing and command/telemetry with ground station. Worked with Xilinx Platform Studio and ISE Design Suite.

NASA Langley Research Center

Hampton, VA

3D Printing Engineer

Jun 2016 - Aug 2016

Mentor: Godfrey Sauti

Leveraged sensor technology to design and improve the dimensional integrity of a printed component using Pronterface. Designed 3D components in Inventor.

PUBLICATIONS Ranjit J., Wang T., Ray B., and Ordonez V. 2023. Variation of Gender Biases in Visual Recognition Models Before and After Finetuning. Neurips 2023 Workshop on Algorithmic Fairness through the Lens of Time. https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07615

> Harder, H., Ranjit J., and Behl M. 2021. Scenario 2Vector: scenario description language based embeddings for traffic situations. Proceedings of the ACM/IEEE 12th International Conference on Cyber-Physical Systems (ICCPS '21). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 167-176. https://doi.org/10.1145/ 3450267.3450544

> Ranjit, J., Behl, Madhur (advisor), & Baritaud, Catherine (advisor) (2020). Scenario2Vec: A Scenario Description Language to Characterize Traffic Scenarios for the Development of a Certification Scheme. University of Virginia, School of Engineering and Applied Science, BS (Bachelor of Science), 2020: Charlottesville, VA. Retrieved from https://doi.org/10.18130/v3-16d9-gn66

PROJECTS & **EXTRA**

Cornell, Maryland, and Max Planck Pre-Doctoral Research School Saarbrücken, Germany

Promising undergraduate and Masters students are invited to attend this program that provides an overview of the state of the art research in Computer Science. Overview of Program

Society of Women Engineers

Charlottesville, VA

Performed service projects at high schools in Charlottesville area to educate minority students about engineering opportunities

Rodman Scholar Charlottesville, VA

Academic honor awarded to top 5% of the engineering class

Project Clear Skies: UVA HooHacks

Charlottesville, VA

Collaborated with Calvin Krist and Grady Roberts to develop a web app using RestAPI that aggregates real time data about a natural disaster from a variety of social media sources giving first responders the ability to perform rapid searches using key words and features. Leveraged Google Vision API and Tensorflow for image classification to provide an accurate assessment of the severity of disasters to reach victims and allocate resources more efficiently. Code Release

Save the Children: UVA Data Science Hackathon Charlottesville, VA Prototyped transformer models in Pytorch for generating infrastructure damage values that can be applied to MDI's predictive analytics model in an effort to better help with displacement efforts due to disasters. Collaborated with Joshua Fitzpatrick to identify a framework for processing twitter data for disaster analytics. Code Release

Truly OpenML

Charlottesville, VA

Led a team of four people to pitch a web application that provides a collaborative, intuitive and accessible platform for individuals who are passionate about learning machine learning (ML). Reached the semifinals at the American Evolution Innovator's Cup. American Evolution Innovator's Cup: Semifinalist

TECHNICAL **SKILLS**

Machine Learning: Tensorflow, Pytorch, Open CV, Numpy, Scikit-learn, Keras, Amazon Web Services

Software: Python, Java, C++, Snowflake, SQL, Django, Agile Methodologies, Git, Heroku, LATEX

REFERENCES

Vicente Ordóñez

Associate Professor Department of Computer Science Rice University vicenteor@rice.edu Madhur Behl

Assistant Professor Department of Computer Science University of Virginia madhur.behl@virginia.edu